Finding Aid for Museums (University of Michigan) Records 1863-1976
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Museums (University of Michigan) records 1863-1976 1930-1970
University of Michigan. Museums.
The Museums was comprised of the Museums of Anthropology, Zoology, and Paleontology, the Herbarium, and the Exhibit Museum. The record group consists of committee files; records related to the construction of the Museums building, including correspondence with architect Albert Kahn; topical files of directors including Alexander Ruthven and Carl Guthe; and topical files of Irving G. Reimann, prefect of exhibits.
86980 Bimu C450
Sponsor: This finding aid is a product of a project supported by a grant awarded to the Bentley Historical Library and University of Michigan Museum of Anthropology in 2002 by the Division of Preservation and Access of the National Endowment for the Humanities, an independent federal agency.
4 linear feet
1 oversize folders
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The record group (donor no. 837 ) was received in multiple accessions beginning in 1939; the largest single accession was received in 1986.
The records are open without restriction.
The practice of retaining specimens for educational purposes is almost as old as the university itself. In 1837, the Regents, acting upon the suggestion of the state legislature, established a "Cabinet of Natural History," making a faculty member responsible for its development and administration. Throughout the nineteenth century responsibility for this activity generally fell upon a faculty member with zoological training. Originally the collections were housed in whatever space could be found for them. Eventually, however, it became necessary to construct a museum to house the material. Occupied in 1880/81, it contained a polyglot mass of specimens, with zoological and anthropological materials being the most numerous.
Towards the end of the nineteenth century, faculty interest in the museums waned, and the institutions stagnated. Beginning in 1903, however, the program was revitalized under Charles C. Adams. In 1906, Adams' leading protégé, Alexander Ruthven, became the driving force behind the Museums. Rapid expansion of various collections led to an appropriation of $900,000 in 1925 for the construction of a new building, which was occupied in 1928.
The administration of the Museums presented the university with a difficult problem. For reasons of economy the university preferred to house all specimen collections under one roof, but the result was a forced marriage of numerous discipline-oriented collections with no common theme. In 1880/81 the regents provided that each collection would have its own discipline-oriented curator who would report to the appropriate department, while the museum building itself would be administered by a custodian. Alexander Ruthven, among others, was sharply critical of this arrangement and in 1913 the Museums' structure was modified with a "Museum of Zoology" being recognized as a unit independent of and equal to the various departments. Despite its name the Museum of Zoology continued to house several disciplinary collections unrelated to zoology.
In 1925, the Regents, preparatory to the construction of a new building, adopted yet another organizational scheme. Four independent units, the Museums of Zoology, Anthropology, and Paleontology, and the Herbarium were all to be housed in a fifth unit, the Museums Building. Ruthven was given two titles, director of the Museum of Zoology and also director of the University Museums Building. In this latter capacity he was responsible for oversight of the building as well as the common services within the building utilized by its four constituent museums. Implemented in 1928 when the new building was occupied, Ruthven resigned his title as director of the Museum of Zoology in 1929, when he assumed the university's presidency, but he retained the title of director of the University Museums Building until 1936, when the press of presidential responsibilities led him to abandon this responsibility. Ruthven was succeeded by Carl E. Guthe, who at the time was already director of the Museum of Anthropology. Guthe left the university in 1944 and control of the building fell to an operating committee composed of the directors of the four units within the structure.
The opening of a new building in 1928 with greatly expanded exhibit space led to a revitalization of the exhibit program. In 1947 the operating committee established the position of prefect of exhibits. Irving G. Reimann, who occupied the post, was responsible for all public exhibits within the building and reported to the operating committee. Reimann, however, grew dissatisfied with this arrangement, and in 1956, in yet another reorganization, an Exhibit Museum was created, co-equal to the constituent museums and with oversight responsibility for all public displays. The General Services Unit of the University Museums Building, formerly under the direction of the Museums Operating Committee, became part of the Exhibit Museum, and reported to the new Museums Building Committee.
The Exhibit Museum reported to the dean of the College of Literature, Science and the Arts (LS&A). The Exhibit Museum consciously decided to expand its presentations beyond the disciplinary bounds of constituent museums and was aided in this process by an Advisory Committee formed within LS&A. Under the auspices of the Exhibit Museum an aggressive program of service to the general public was begun.
The records of the University of Michigan Museums measure four linear feet (and one oversize folder) and date from 1863 to 1976. The great majority of the material, however, falls between 1930 and 1970. The files have been arranged alphabetically.
The bulk of the material consists of files created from two sources: various committees involved in the Museums' governance or Irving Reimann. The committee records are detailed and are particularly complete for the Operating Committee (1945-1956). This committee's documentation is supplemented by various other committee records.
Most of the records created by Reimann relate to the planning or construction of exhibits, as well as the public role of the Museums. This material makes up the bulk of the non-committee files, supplemented by an extensive run of reports (1935-1969). A few records created before Reimann's appointment also exist. These are generally items authored by either Guthe or Ruthven. Of particular interest from Ruthven's era are files (located under "Building") discussing the construction of the Museums building between 1925 and 1928. Records include substantive correspondence between Ruthven and the building's architect, Albert Kahn. Guthe is represented by the Works Progress Administration's Michigan Museum project (located under "Works Progress Administration, Statewide Museum Project").
Subjects:
University of Michigan. Museums.; United States. Works Progress Administration. Statewide Museum Survey.; University of Michigan--Buildings.; University of Michigan--Exhibitions.; University Museums Building (University of Michigan); Architects.; Architecture--Michigan.
Contributors:
Guthe, Carl E. (Carl Eugen), 1893-1974; Kahn, Albert, 1869-1942.; Reimann, Irving G.; Ruthven, Alexander Grant, 1882-1971.
- Topical Files 1863-1976
  - A-General (Box 1)
  - American Association of Museums
    - General 1952-1956 (Box 1)
    - Annual Meeting in Detroit 1940 (Box 1)
    - Museum Training Committee 1958-1962 (Box 1)
  - Angell, Carleton 1926-1950 (Box 1)
  - Ann Arbor: Community Use of Museum 1957-1962 (Box 1)
  - Anthropology 1916-1939 (Box 1)
  - Art Museum 1933-1950 (Box 1)
  - B-General (Box 1)
  - Bibliographies of Museums Publications circa 1945 (Box 1)
  - Budget 1946-1955, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Building
    - 1879-1894 (Box 1)
    - General Correspondence re 1911-1930 (Box 1)
    - Construction of Building 1926-1927
      - Specifications, 3 folders (Box 1)
      - Room Plans (Box 1)
      - Furniture and Equipment (Box 1)
      - Mechanical Trades-Bids (Box 1)
      - General Plans and Specifications, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Maintenance 1936-1951 (Box 1)
  - Bulletins to Staff 1936-1956 (Box 1)
  - Collections 1888-1926 (Box 1)
  - Committees
    - Advisory Board 1945-1956, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Advisory Committee 1941-1945 (Box 1)
    - Advisory Committee of the Exhibit Museum 1956-1969 (Box 1)
    - Advisory Committee on Museum Exhibits 1954-1955 (Box 1)
    - Building Committee 1956-1964 (Box 1)
    - Exhibits Committee 1933-1939 (Box 1)
    - Library Committee 1946-1957 (Box 1)
    - Operating Committee 1945-1956
      - Chairman Files 1954-1956 (Box 2)
      - Correspondence 1948, 1952-1956 (Box 2)
      - Minutes 1945-1956, 3 folders (Box 2)
      - Miscellaneous 1946-1956 (Box 2)
    - Reserves Committee 1939-1948 (Box 2)
  - Cummings, Virginia 1971-1972 (Box 2)
  - D-General 1943-1965 (Box 2)
  - Development Council 1958-1972 (Box 2)
  - Dinosaur Purchase 1960 (Box 2)
  - Division of the Biological Sciences
    - Annual Reports 1948-1951 (Box 2)
    - Committees
      - General 1948-1953 (Box 2)
      - Research 1948-1950 (Box 2)
      - Space Requirements 1948-1953 (Box 2)
      - Teaching 1948-1953 (Box 2)
    - Memo re Museum Titles 1954 (Box 2)
    - Status of Research 1950-1953 (Box 2)
  - Docents 1939-1951 (Box 2)
  - Exhibits
    - General 1933-1954 (Box 2)
    - Philosophy of at University of Michigan undated (term paper) (Box 2)
    - Photographs of (Box 2)
  - Exhibits Section 1933-1972 (Box 2)
  - F-General 1939 (Box 2)
  - Fish Front News 1943-1945 (Box 2)
  - Formal Opening of Buildings 1928 (Box 2)
  - H-General 1938-1950 (Box 2)
  - Hall of Evolution 1954-1965 (Box 2)
  - Herbarium 1924-1958 (Box 2)
  - Institute for Fisheries Research 1940-1951 (Box 2)
  - K-General 1938-1953 (Box 2)
  - L-General 1939-1958 (Box 2)
  - M-General 1947-1973 (Box 3)
  - Marchand, George 1947-1967 (Box 3)
  - Marchand, Paul 1949-1971 (Box 3)
  - Michigan Audubon Society: Publication Index 1951-1952 (Box 3)
  - Michigan Historical Commission 1924-1926 (Box 3)
  - Missaukee Preserve 1923-1954 (Archaeological Site) (Box 3)
  - Mosaic 1938-1942 (Box 3)
  - Museum Descriptive Booklet 1929 (Box 3)
  - Museum Guides undated, 1937 (Box 3)
  - Museum Methods Course 1938-1943 (Box 3)
  - Museum Program: Five Year Plan 1946 (Box 3)
  - National Museum of Canada 1957-1958 (Box 3)
  - Notes on History of circa 1943-1953 (Box 3)
    (compiled by Carl Guthe)
  - Olson Studies 1948-1955 (Box 3)
  - P-Q-General 1936-1972 (Box 3)
  - Paleontology, Museum of 1937-1939 (Box 3)
  - Personnel circa 1945 (Box 3)
  - Photographic Laboratory, Need for 1880 (Box 3)
  - Place of Museums in University Organization 1947 (Box 3)
  - Planetarium notes re Viking Space Probe 1976 (Box 3)
  - Program posters and building miscellanea, 1 oversize folders (Folder 1)
    (Bimu C450)
  - Prefect Search 1947 (Box 3)
  - Press Releases 1947-1951 (Box 3)
  - Professional and Administrative Salary Study, Museums and Libraries 1972 (Box 3)
  - Promotion of Museum 1958-1974 (Box 3)
  - Radio-carbon Dating Exhibit (includes photos) 1957-1958 (Box 3)
  - Regental By-law Revision 1939-1940 (Box 3)
  - Reiber, Edwin H. 1947-1956 (Box 3)
  - Reimann, Irving H.
    - Appointment 1946-1947 (Box 3)
    - Correspondence 1947-1974 (Box 3)
    - Publications 1937-1974 (Box 3)
  - Re-organization of Museums 1955-1956 (Box 3)
  - Reports
    - General 1863-1911 (Box 3)
    - Annual
      - Drafts and Data 1935-1969, 17 folders (Box 3)
      - Published Reports 1936-1957, 3 folders (Box 4)
      - Exhibit Section 1948-1950 (Box 4)
    - Service Unit Reports 1937-1951, 3 folders (Box 4)
  - Rhodes, Frank H.T. 1971-1974 (Box 4)
  - Rodeck, Hugo G. 1950-1961 (Box 4)
  - S-General 1952-1970 (Box 4)
  - Smithsonian 1947-1959 (Box 4)
  - Space
    - Distribution of 1947-1954 (Box 4)
    - Division of Biological Sciences Report on 1957 (Box 4)
    - Needs 1939 (Box 4)
  - Special Events 1950-1955, 9 folders (Box 4)
  - Staff Memos 1955-1972 (Box 4)
  - Staff Survey 1940-1942 (Box 4)
  - T-General 1950-1973 (Box 4)
  - Taxidermist 1937 (Box 4)
  - Tour Groups, photos circa 1972 (Box 4)
  - U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service 1939-1949 (Box 4)
  - Vertebrate Biology, Laboratory of 1937-1950 (Box 4)
  - Visitors to Museum
    - Attendance 1947-1955 (Box 4)
    - Registers March 1, 1929-December 8, 1929, 2 volumes (Box 4)
    - Survey of 1956 (Box 4)
  - Visual Education 1936-1947 (Box 4)
  - W-Z-General 1950-1972 (Box 4)
  - Works Progress Administration, Statewide Museums Project 1938-1939, 1943, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Zoology, Museum of 1937-1946 (Box 4)